[Music]
This is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the e
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Fly machines from fly.io are
fastaunching hardware isolated virtual
machines that spin up in milliseconds.
They're the perfect place to deploy even
the sketchiest user or LLM generated
code. If something breaks, just spin up
a fresh machine and you're good to go.
Plus, Fly Machines scale to zero when
they're not needed, so you only pay for
what you use. Fly.io. Built by humans,
loved by robots.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Pijh Amanut. Today I will
be discussing autonomous testing with
Wilhelm Fawn Erinheim. Wilhelm is the
co-founder and chief AI officer of
QA.te, a startup that develops
autonomous agents that can interact and
test the functionality of web pages. He
has over 10 years of experience in data
science and machine learning domain.
Before co-ounding QA.te, Wilhelm built
Mother Brain at EQT. Wilhelm has
published papers in prestigious
conferences such as EMNLP, KDDD and
CIKM.
Wilhelm, welcome to the show. Thank you.
I'm very glad to be here. We'll start
with the fundamentals. If you can help
by defining what is autonomous testing
and how does it differ from traditional
automated testing. I'd like to think of
the testing in the levels of autonomy in
different stages. So the first stage is
manual testing where nothing is really
automated. You're just doing everything
as a human and try to potentially repeat
the same thing again as you have done
before. The next stage is where you
start using automation. So scripts or
different kinds of programs that can
repeatedly do the same things over and
over. That has been popularized by tools
like Cypress, Selenium and and
Playright. Today we see more and more
things that comes into a new category
called autonomous testing where we level
up the level of autonomy even more. So
instead of it being hard-coded scripts,
you focus more on either self-healing so
that you can kind of don't have to spend
as much time developing and maintaining
the test suites that you have or you
have fully autonomous agents that can
understand and validate different kinds
of objectives that you want the page to
to support.
Right. Can you expand on that a bit more
and maybe walk us through the evolution
of software testing? How did it evolve
from manual to automated and now to
autonomous?
Yeah, I think the manual side of thing
comes pretty natural when you have built
something that you want to ship to a
potential customer or a user. You want
to make sure that it works. And this is
something that I think most developers
are very accustomed to. You try the
different features that you have built.
You click around or you interact with it
in different ways to make sure that it
functions the way that you have
intended.
The automation of that comes natural. So
when you have different ways that you
want to test your software, usually you
use different kinds of testing in
different layers. So you have things
like unit tests, testing specific
snippets of code. You have integration
tests making sure that stuff works
across different systems. Then you have
the end to end tests where you script
that something is working in the browser
or in the application or something and
kind of program hardcode those steps. So
for example, maybe you have a
possibility to send an invoice in your
system or do a checkout for example.
Then you script what should be filled in
and you make sure that it clicks on the
right buttons and and then you wait and
try to validate that it went through as
expected.
On the autonomous side, first of all,
the automated tests are pretty hard to
maintain. When you think about
hard-coded things in general, they're
very brittle to change. And what's
problematic with scripting something and
testing that against a system that is
continuously evolving and changing is
that then those tests will continuously
break. So when you build a new feature
or you change something in your checkout
flow then suddenly all of your tests are
failing not because it's no longer
functioning but because they no longer
do the right things or the buttons have
changed or the identifiers on the page
are not the same anymore.
And that then requires the developer to
go back to that code and also update the
test suites to make sure that they they
kind of adhere to the new changes that
you've made. On the autonomous level, we
try to mitigate that by erasing the
abstraction one more layer. Again, AI
and machine learning systems are
essentially designed to be able to
handle a vast kind of range of changing
input parameters and still produce like
a reasonable answer. So essentially
generalizing across a lot of different
potential things that could happen which
is the same as a human would do. So for
example if I add an extra button in a
step in a checkout then I wouldn't fail
the test because I understand that oh
that's a new button and I can take a
decision not to click it or interact
with it in different ways and still be
able to complete the checkout. And this
is where AI comes in in as well. If we
change the application in any of the
numerous ways that we normally do when
we develop them, it's then possible to
let the AI understand and take decisions
in real time when it's doing the testing
instead of having to rely on updating
all of these tests that we have created
before. Mhm. And that is what you meant
by self-healing tests.
Yes, exactly. There is like two
categories here. There are those that
focus more on automatically updating the
test scripts that are available or there
are those that rely more on agentic
systems that take the decision in real
time as you see it. So either you kind
of analyze the changes and and handle
those changes in a nicer way in in your
automated testing scripts or you have an
agent or an AI that can actually
interpret the page and understand that
we're trying to do the checkout. We're
testing whether or not the checkout is
working. Then if a new button comes up
or if it changes colors or if it's
moving around to another location on the
page, it's still able to navigate there
and perform the checkout to ensure that
it works. We will deep dive into agents
and how they function in a later
section. But before that, I just wanted
to cover a few more fundamental
questions. You mentioned tools like
Selenium, JUnit, Cypress that are used
for automated testing.
What are some of the popular tools for
autonomous testing and how mature are
they? So, there's more and more tools
coming out. There's some that have been
around for a while that are adding more
AI features on top of them. So for
example, you have tools like Apply tools
that has had kind of guey based way to
be able to do or low code sorry way to
to kind of do testing where you have
different kinds of steps and instead of
then relying on a specific identifier
you could use AI steps and things like
that instead that can kind of analyze
just that specific step. Then there are
tools like QA techch where I work that
run even a higher kind of abstra level
of abstraction when we we use agents
instead. And there are a few other
competitors of ours and and similar
tools that are coming out now and I
would say the maturity is still in the
earlier stages when it comes to agentic
based testing but we're definitely
moving closer and closer to that being a
very mature area as well. All right. And
are most of the tools focused on the UI
layer? There are different tools for
different layers. So you do have when it
comes to unit test and integration
testing and API testing, there's has
been like a suite of tools for this over
a long time as well using AI to do to
help you write good unit tests for
example. That is something that has
naturally been evolving as AI gets
better and better at coding. We also see
some tools that are kind of evolving
around API testing and making more smart
features around that as well. But where
we I think the testing community have
been struggling the most has been in the
end to end testing where like we test
the full application where everything is
kind of coming together which is also
where sometimes really strange things
can happen because if you test something
you should test something very kind of
isolated and specific so you understand
what's functioning and what's not for
that component. But when you put all of
those components together is where
something gets to be very hard to test
and also much more prone to errors. And
are there testing scenarios where manual
testing still plays a critical role?
Yes, I think so. I think we will see
more and more evolution in this space.
But there is um a concept of exploratory
testing that is still pretty new uh when
it comes to AI features. There are
features where an AI can kind of try
different things and interact with with
it in in a in a less kind of planned
manner, but I think there's still
definitely a space for humans both in
the exploratory side, but also to ensure
the entire kind of quality process of
your development flow. We can talk more
about explorative testing. But in
general, that is when you have certain
area and you kind of explore all the
different kinds of edge or kind of a
surface boundaries around that feature
and what could potentially change if you
change states and land in different kind
of ways which I definitely still think
there is need for humans to be involved.
Right. Do you have any examples or
stories of where companies have
transitioned and implemented autonomous
testing? what was their journey like?
Yeah, so we have a number of clients
that have been transitioning more into
autonomous testing and you would see
some different categories in there. One
of our customers were having both a
suite of automated tests and a team of
QA engineers that were both kind of
building these and doing manual testing.
They had to let go some of their
engineers during during the financial
crisis. So kind of had this much smaller
team and that team then over the years
had a very hard hard time kind of
keeping up with the the need for all the
testing that they had. So they partnered
with us and were able to to kind of
speed up their team so that their team
could do more interesting things and not
only do these repetitive tasks in the
browser and managed to to reduce their
testing costs drastically. How does a
human prove that AI generated tests
work? So this is slightly different
depending on the tools I would say but
in general when you look at QCH as a
tool we we try to be as transparent
about the AI's reasoning and its kind of
execution paths as possible. So as a
human when you get like a bug report or
something similar from from either a
manual or kind of tester or or an
automated script, what's important in
order to be able to debug and kind of
deep dive into those issues that have
been encountered is to have a full
recording of the session and as much
data as possible of the session. Ideally
recording that's not only always the
case with especially manual but but even
in automated testing it's hard to do
sometimes. So I think it's equally
important in the autonomous testing to
be very transparent about what's
happening and show as much of the
underlying kind of functionality on the
page as possible. So we show the full
recording of the the session with all
the steps and the reasoning that the
agent has taken in all of the different
steps. You could also see console logs,
network logs, and all of these different
things that could potentially show why
something has happened and make it
easier for an engineer to reproduce and
then subsequently fix. Right? Coming
back to the example where the company
transitioned over to autonomous testing.
There the constraint was primarily lack
of capacity amongst the testing team.
But are there prerequisites that a
company should consider before they
consider autonomous testing? Whether
that's from a technology front or does
it work with legacy technology or from
infrastructure perspective does is there
a minimum power from an infrastructure
perspective which needs to be looked at
before you consider autonomous testing.
In general you need to have some kind of
environment for the agents to run in. So
from the infrastructure side, you need
to have an isolated environment that the
agent can work in that is like reachable
and you have the functionality that you
want to test in. So for example, if you
only develop your local machine and then
go to production, then maybe there isn't
really an environment that you have that
we could test things in. I would say
that that is pretty bad practice in
general. But if you do, then that might
be hard to to use most of those
autonomous testing tools. Then you would
have to look for something that can run
locally on your machine instead. Another
thing that is a prerequisite in general
is that you I think you need to have
like some kind of problem to start with
like either you don't really have any
testing and you would like to upgrade
your testing and start kind of building
out the test suite so that you can
ensure that your functionality is as
should or you have like a a large suite
of autonomous tests and you have a
problem kind of maintaining them and it
takes a lot of time and effort then then
you have that kind of specific
thing in mind to start trying to
optimize against or you have manual QA
and it's expensive or they have a hard
time keeping up. So I think you should
look at those different cases slightly
differently like you have a problem then
you know what you're trying to kind of
achieve with implementing another
solution and then you can kind of track
those metrics and see that you're
actually succeeding with your
implementation. Right. And from a
technology perspective, are there
constraints where to give an example
maybe does autonomous testing work on
software which has APIs? So if you have
a legacy technology which does not
provide APIs, would autonomous testing
still work over there? Our solution
would work with it as long as it's
browser based. I think there are new
tools coming out for more native
applications as well. have been
discussing supporting that in the long
horizon. But currently we only support
browser based applications. So you need
to have like some kind of URL where this
page is deployed and you can let the
agent interact with the with the page.
When it comes to APIs, like if you only
have a specific set of APIs and things,
I think you should look at other tools
for for that specific thing. There's a
lot of different kinds of ways to
automate and test APIs in a good way. I
would say you could definitely use AI
for that today in order to help discover
different kinds of potential inputs for
the API that you could so that you can
cover a larger kind of set of the
potential surface area. We'll move on to
the next section which is we'll deep
dive into autonomous testing and we'll
also explore the role of agents. Let's
start off maybe if you can explain the
essential components of an autonomous
testing system. Yeah. So we focus on the
agentic systems specifically. Normally
what you would have to have as a
component as different components in
this system is as all a agents you
essentially need to have some kind of
core processing model that could could
look at input and produce output for you
and then you would have a way to for
that kind of system to be able to
observe the environment which in this
case is the browser. So you would have
to have some kind of browser component
that can feed back information about the
page that is relevant for the agent to
take good decisions. And then you
usually also need some kind of memory
component that can record and store
information that is relevant for the
agent to keep as it continues along its
trajectory. And still I would say today
you usually need some kind of planning
component as well. You could either do
that with with AI or you can kind of do
other kind of smarter planning solutions
as well using machine learning or
search. But in general, in order to be
able to produce a good test trajectory,
you need to have information about this
the system that you're running against
so that it can plan a potential test
execution beforehand and then kind of
evolve through that with the agents.
Right? So to summarize, you need at
least four components. You have the core
processing model which is EI model. You
have a component which observes the
environment. You have the memory
component. I believe that's where the
selfhealing and learning will happen.
And then you have the planning where the
test trae trajectory or the test cases
are planned. Yes, exactly. I also forgot
to mention there that you need to be
able to execute things in the
environment otherwise nothing is going
to happen. So you also need the
possibility to let the core processing
execute commands in the browser. You
also mentioned that you were going to
focus on agentic systems for autonomous
testing. What are the other types of
autonomous testing systems?
I briefly mentioned that earlier that
there are a few different solutions that
focus more on self-healing of of the
hard-coded tests. So you would for
example have a hard-coded test run and
then you would have like a recorded
session of how that looks and then you
can use AI models to selfheal if
something has changed which is not
necessarily a real error. So then then
say for example in the case of the
checkout if you added another step then
instead of it being being broken and you
would have to fix it manually you would
have an AI assist you in fixing that
automatically and analyzing whether or
not it was a reasonable failure or not.
And then um there are also other tools.
There's a newer uh startup called
meticulous as well that does something
similar where they rather analyze
different changes in the in the
rendering of the of the different pages.
So they they look at smaller changes and
try to analyze whether or not that is
kind of intended or not. And then you
also have a another category where they
primarily focus on analyzing user
sessions. So then if you record user
sessions like is common place in in
different product discovery
tools like u like full story or similar
then
you could look at those sessions and
then identify whether a user actually
has encountered a bug as well. So
letting AI look at the session and see
oh there was an error there. What are AI
agents in the context of autonomous
testing?
So AI agents are a way for us to be able
to
execute tests and analyze and take
decisions as they move. When you take
the examples that we said before, like
if something unexpected happens, then a
normal test would not have the
possibility to recover from that.
Whereas an AI agent has the possibility
to both observe and take decisions and
take actions in the system, right? So
then if something unexpected happens
like for for example something is
missing or something has moved or
something like then it has the
possibility to analyze whether or not
that was kind of intended change or
whether or not it was actually some kind
of bug and then it can also have the
possibility to then take decisions on
what to do next without necessarily
knowing up front what it was supposed to
do. So it can in the case when some when
we added a new step to the checkout then
it can identify oh there is this new
step here in the checkout that I need to
fill in. maybe I need to fill in more
information about the user or something
and then it can fill in that information
and then move onwards with the test as
if was kind of programmed to do that
from the start since it's much better at
taking decisions and understanding
different kinds of contexts. Can you
walk us through a specific instance
where an AI agent adopted to a changing
application without needing manual
intervention?
Do you have any examples around such use
cases? We have seen so many examples of
these which is which is pretty cool.
It's one of the things that I think is
the most fun to see when and develop
agents for one instance. For example, we
had we usually have a suite of login
tests and then when you kind of come
into the application we have more tests
in there. Those login tests are usually
kind of the dependencies for the rest.
And we had one of our customers who
completely changed their login provider.
So instead of it being like a a username
password login that they had hardcoded
themselves, they used another third
party one to support more different
kinds of login scenarios and our agents
have were able to run this like
completely transparently without any
kind of problems at all. We had another
example where one of our customers has
like a management system for e-commerce
store where they have different where
you have the possibility to kind of
create warehouses and change stock in
there and so forth. And there was some
test where it should continue to
configure the warehouse and then for
some reason like something else has
happened where they had reset the
database. So there was no data for it to
actually test run the tests on where
instead of failing the test then the
agent actually went in and created a new
warehouse and then continued onwards to
configure it and concluded that that the
configuration is still functioning as it
should. Very interesting.
How do agents decide which test to run
and what areas of the application to
focus on? This I think is a very
interesting area and we have decided to
focus on
analyzing the page and and kind of
understanding the different components
that exist in an application and then
ask the user whether or not they want to
test those things. So in our platform
you have the possibility to
kind of create high level objectives
like in the warehouse case it should be
possible to configure the warehouse or
in the checkout it should possible to to
purchase something and kind of check out
the system and uh and then when we kind
of execute those we discover more and
more data about those things and then we
can suggest new different kinds of test
cases that you could potentially add to
your regression suite.
And that could be for example, it should
be possible then to add like your cart
to some kind of favorites list or store
it for later or should be possible to
delete the warehouse if you haven't had
tests for those. And then as you as we
run more things and we have analyzed the
page more and more, we come up more and
more things like this that could be
interesting for you to test and add to
your test suite. But we we rely still on
humans to actually kind of take that
final decision whether or not they want
to run those things.
And how do the agents handle test data
generation?
AI in general is really good at coming
up with things. If you ask Chachi to
write you a poem, it will do so with a
brilliant job. And we see the same thing
when it comes to data generation for
different test scenarios. So even when
it's very specific. So you have things
like this warehouse that I mentioned
where you have to come up with a lot of
different configuration options and very
specific details for their specific
system. But if you give an AI enough
context about what it is that it's
looking at and what you want to get out
from there. So for example, I want I
want to get generate example data for
this form and this page is doing this
and that and this is the warehouses and
they have all of these different
configurations and so forth. It would be
very good at coming up with interesting
test data to use for those scenarios,
right? And also is there a risk of bias
creeping in because AI is generating the
data? Yes, there is definitely a risk or
bias in general when it comes to AI
generated content. I think what you then
need to be very mindful about is to to
help it get the right context that would
make sense for your application and the
different things that you would like it
to to think about. But there is always
definitely a risk of it being very kind
of say for example only generating names
in a from a certain kind of western
country or something and not thinking
about the different kind of cultures and
things that that could potentially be
using the platform. And what does bias
mean from a autonomous testing
perspective? Does it mean that certain
test cases are completely excluded and
not run and hence there are gaps in the
testing? There's definitely a risk for
that in general. Well, I think you have
the same risk with with humans running
testing as well that they have a
specific kind of mentality in how they
run different tests or how they test
different applications. Maybe one QA
tester is much more interested in
testing SQL injections whereas another
one is much more interested in in
manipulating state of the application
for in general. I think we haven't seen
too much problems in that when it comes
to testing it from uh higher level
objectives that the especially when you
focus on kind of I want this specific
warehouse functionality to to work in
this and that way and make sure that
that it kind of fulfills these things.
But there's definitely always a risk of
it not kind of thinking of some specific
thing and doing the same tests over and
over again in a more kind of biased
manner than maybe you do. But it still
opens up I think for more variation and
possibilities to variate and kind of
test the application more closely to how
a user actually experience your
application compared to normal auton
test automation where you hardcode a
specific steps even there and if you
generate data for that or kind of come
up with a lot of different data it's
still very much more limited right I was
just comparing that to a normal say
manual plus automated testing
combination.
Uh if you had a tester which who was
focused primarily on SQL injection, you
would ideally have the test plan which
would ensure that all these areas are
covered. Yes, exactly. Whereas in
autonomous testing, I'm assuming the
test plan itself is prepared by AI. So
how do you what approach do you take to
identify the biases and identify the
misses the areas that have been missed
from testing?
Yeah, we rely on test plans as well. So,
uh, essentially what we help the user
with is kind of coming up with different
test plans and then executing those test
plans. But you still have the
possibility to work with your test
plans. So, if you specify that something
should function in a certain way and
that you expect it to load within a
certain amount of time and uh that it
should be possible to do something else
after that. say for after a checkout for
example, you should get an email. As
long as you have those things specified
in your plan, I think you can definitely
be very confident that the AI will do
the same thing. But of course, having a
complete coverage of your entire
application and thinking of all the
different ways that you would want to
test it is a challenging subject. Mhm.
What techniques are used to optimize
test execution?
There there are different ways that you
can optimize the execution when it comes
to agents. And the first thing is to
collect more context for for them so
that they can kind of understand and
execute things in a in a smarter way.
And then the other thing that you could
work on is this kind of planning
component where it comes to
understanding and doing things with a
better plan usually increase the
performance quite a bit. Then there is
also the possibility to do different
kinds of fine-tuning. So for example, if
you have very specific application that
maybe h haven't been and nothing similar
has been seen in the training data of
the of the larger models that are are
kind of taking the decisions then they
might perform really really badly. And
if you then collect data on those things
and train your your agent to it could be
that you train different components or
if you train this kind of main execution
engine or model to better be able to
analyze and take good decisions in that
environment, right?
What will make it maybe a bit more
clearer is maybe we think it think of it
from an interventions perspective.
So if you have autonomous testing
implemented, what are the various
interventions where you need the test
team to either help set it up either
from a collecting the context or in
planning or in fine-tuning. So what are
the ways interventions where you need
intervention or some actual human doing
something to
make sure the autonomous testing is
working as expected
in general when it comes to to AI
systems and I think this applies here as
well is that you need to uh observe some
data in order to make sure if you have
false positives or false negatives. If
you do encounter like a false positive,
say that for example, it was not
possible to check out but the agent kind
of completed the test anyway or if you
have the other type of failure where you
the agent kind of struggled with
something and say that it wasn't
possible to do the check out even though
it is a functioning feature. What you
don't would have to do is to to uh
report those. So it slightly depends on
the tool that you're using on how you
could potentially do this. But in
general what you need to do is to
feedback those issues and then m that
makes it possible for the agent to
learn. So that could either be using
different
mechanisms like reflection which is a
way for the agent to kind of analyze
positive and negative pairs and kind of
come up with a with a better way to
think about the problem. or it could be
through fine-tuning where you could
actually use those as labels. When it
comes to kind of reinforcement learning
in general, you also have the
possibility to do training with
verifiable tasks. So if you have a
system where you have the possibility to
know whether or not it actually
succeeded from an outside kind of
perspective, then you can use that data
as well to train the agents to come up
with better planning or better execution
strategies. Right. What what are the
some of the biggest challenges in
training AI agents? I think it is a
pretty new tech in general. So the
evolution in the AI field has been super
rapid over the last few years but we
have still it has been taking quite a
bit of time before we've seen agents
actually being firstirhand citizen in
the training. So now today you have
tools like entropic has released
computer use and openAI has released
their operator and different agent
frameworks which has put a lot of more
effort on an emphasis on training these
models based on inputs that are
interface based. So when we look a few
years back then large language models
were not trained on this. They were
primarily trained on text conversations
and when they started to be multimodal
they were mostly trained on
different kinds of images of of uh the
real world and not so much of
interfaces. And we had a lot of
struggles in the beginning where those
models were were struggling a lot to
identify simple things that a human find
very simple in an interface like for
example if the uh pages in dark mode or
light mode or where different buttons
are if you should hover or if you should
click things and all of these things but
it has become a lot better over the last
year I would say. Have you come across
cases where agents failed or struggled
to execute a test properly? What was the
root cause and how was it fixed?
Usually that boils down to the agent not
having context or it being a complicated
flow in some way such that it's hard for
the agent to understand what it's
supposed to do. It sometimes can be the
simple things but most of the times it's
when it's the flow is very long and
complicated and you it needs some kind
of knowledge that is hard for the agent
of have in its context.
But we have seen things where like in
the earlier days it struggled a lot with
even simpler things like a certain date
picker being implemented in a weird way
or things like that. But how we kind of
overcome that in general is to to
identify problematic areas and then try
to collect more data on those and and
improve our listening structure in order
to to learn the agent how to solve those
things. Sometimes it could also be
issues with how the browser is
interpreting things and how we kind of
translate things from the browser to the
agent. So there's there's those kind of
areas that you might need to improve as
well. Right. And are there common
integration pitfalls that teams should
watch out for? Do you have any stories
or examples around
around such cases? You mean in general
like integration when you've integrated
autonomous testing to an existing uh you
know test flow? I think where we have
seen the agent struggle is where you
have uh very complicated uh
applications. So some of the things that
we have had a hard time testing is when
you for example have a very complex
management system and that affects
another system and you want to kind of
ensure that those things are happening
at the same time which is uh which is
hard to do in autonomous testing as
well. And I think if the system is is
very complicated and hard to understand
for a human it will be even harder for
an agent. So that I I think that's still
the case even though we're moving
rapidly forward. So I I think if it is a
very complicated hard application that
is kind of hard to come up with test
easily written test plans for it then I
think it might be hard for the agency to
succeed.
Right. We'll move to the next section
where I want to discuss transitioning to
autonomous testing. So how should teams
approach integrating autonomous testing
into their existing workflows?
I think we see a lot of evolution in the
development workflows in general today
where more and more AI tools are coming
in and I think you should approach it
with some kind of curiosity at first. So
even if you have a rigorous suite of
autonomous tests and you have a good
team of QA engineers, there's still a
possibility for you to level up your
testing and make it even more covering.
And what you could potentially do is to
just start out with a certain subset of
things that you that maybe your QA team
don't want to focus on as much. And
maybe you have some set of smoke tests
or something that you want to run on
each deploy that takes a lot of time to
maintain for example or then maybe you
should try to use AI to solve some of
those issues. I think in general what my
recommendation would be to just to give
it a go and see if it suits your
workflow. I think we will move more and
more into a development workflow that
has a lot of AI assisted components. So
if you for example are curious about
code generation and uh using agents for
solving bugs in your ticketing system
then I think that complements really
well with using AI assisted testing as
well because then you could kind of
discover different kinds of bugs which
is very hard for for code based agents
or or know code solutions to to do
actually and then you can complement
that with a testing solution that they
can kind of feed
interesting issues and problems into
your ticketing system and then use
modern AI coding solutions to to solve
some of those features. Mhm.
Can you tell me about the key technical
and organizational challenges any client
of yours has faced in adopting
autonomous testing?
Um
I think we have had some clients that
have had technical challenges where it
comes to how they run their development
flows. If you like if you only have uh
feature branches for example and no
specific QA environment run and that has
definitely been problematic.
We have had some customers run instead
these agents as kind of monitoring
solution on your production environment.
that's possible, but I would say still
it's it's more optimized towards running
and being able to kind of report issues
in your staging before you actually do
the the the deployment. And any
organizational challenges come to mind?
So organizationally,
I would say that the teams that struggle
the most are are when you don't really
have any kind of testing efforts already
because then you need to kind of come up
with what you what you actually want to
do and how you kind of structure things.
I think the teams where you already have
maybe one or two QAs or you have
engineers that are used to kind of
automated testing then it's usually very
well received because they have the
similar setup already.
We do see some kind of QA teams being
being a little bit hesitant to to take
in automated solutions. I think it's
partly because they feel like they're
being replaced, but I would much more
like to think of it as a way to get
superpowers. It's the same with
analytics tools or or forecasting suites
for for for financial department. It's
not necessarily replacing those that did
it by hand. It's just like makes them so
much smarter and better. And I think you
could do the same in in QA testing. So
if you have the possibility to hand off
some of those repetitive things that you
have to do all the time to an AI agent,
then that makes it much easier for you
to focus on other things and and uh move
faster.
And do you have any examples where any
particular client could not successfully
implement autonomous testing?
The examples that I have seen has been
either because of their kind of
implementation. So for example, some
system have a very kind of complicated
authentication flows that only needs to
function with the KYC solution in that
country for example or you have some
kind of technical limitation on how you
can run things and maybe your data is
very sensitive also in your staging
environment for example and we have had
some customers that have had to kind of
step away from using it because they
didn't want to share that data. When you
say technical limitations around data,
is it are you referring to masked data?
Yeah. So, it kind of depends on the way
that you structure things. Usually what
we would recommend is to have some kind
of staging environment where you don't
have sensitive data. But some systems
have a hard time kind of having test
data in that kind of environment where
there is data that you haven't lost in
the staging environment or or obiscated
or changed in some way. and and then you
have if you have a regulatory kind of
requirement to to not share that data
then it's of course hard to use tools
that that kind of analyze and uh execute
that data right and what metrics should
teams track to measure the success of
autonomous testing
I think there are several interesting
metrics that you could track I think
first of all when it comes to test
execution time you could measure
how long it takes for you to run your
entire test suites. If you have a lot of
manual work in there, it usually takes
quite a long time. So if you have the
possibility to remove some of that time
and make your cycles shorter, then
that's it's an interesting metric to
measure. It also if you have more of an
automated testing suite, it's
interesting to analyze the ratio of
flaky tests. So if you see some if you
implement more autonomous solutions you
usually see some kind of reduction in
the fake test ratio. Then of course the
holy grail is the the bug detection
rate. So if you how many of bugs do you
actually discover and uh and kind of
prohibit using different kinds of
testing tools. I think those are are
super interesting to test all of them.
Okay, before we move to the next
section, if you can just quickly explain
to our listeners what are flaky tests.
Yeah, so flaky tests are in general uh a
test that is failing every now and then
intermittently
without actually being a real failure.
So usually in automated testing that
could be that there is like a network
hiccup or uh the page takes slightly
longer to load than what is what is kind
of loaded in.
There are a lot of different reasons
that could potentially be the reason for
driving a leak test, but you usually see
that a lot in especially in end to end
testing because the environment has so
many different variables and different
states. So, it's usually very hard to
hardcode a test that takes all of those
kind of things into account. That's also
why autonomous testing can can help you
reduce those.
Right? So in my mind's eye, if I was
scripting it out in an automated
fashion, I would say know the page could
take x amount of time. So I would put in
a weight condition and sometimes that
weight condition could be more than
required or less than required. Whereas
in an automous fashion, the AI agent
would decide how long to wait. Maybe,
you know, it would take into factor the
network speed and other factors into
consideration. Exactly. It also at least
our agent is also kind of gets visual
cues on the on the page. So if you have
like a loader that is still spinning
then uh then it understands that it
should wait a little bit longer. Of
course if it takes too long and it times
out then it will see those things and
then which is a real failure. But if
it's just like something that took a
little bit longer than usual then uh
Yep. makes sense. We'll move on to the
next section which is the human element
in autonomous testing. So in real world
implementation
implementations how has autonomous
testing changed the role of QA or test
engineers?
So I think when you are a manual QA
tester then you usually have a lot of
different things that you would like to
test in the platform and that that could
be very manual. So every time you do a
larger suite of of tests then then you
would have to do the same thing.
So that definitely changes right. I
think you it would be more like a QA
manager in a way that actually kind of
comes up with interesting test plans and
make sure that the AI is executing all
of those things and kind of work
together with AI to come up with
different test strategies to improve
your coverage and and uh when it comes
to uh the engineers that are normally
developing all the autonomous tests,
they usually welcome this improvement
because they need to spend a lot less
time on writing and fixing primarily
maintaining those kind of flaky tests
that break over time when your
application change. Have companies found
that testers need to upskill to work
alongside AIdriven testing tools. Uh
what specific skills are required and
how can testers go about upskilling
themselves?
I think I don't think there is any
specific need in upskilling per se, but
there is of course a need for upskilling
in understanding what tools are
available today and how you could
potentially use modern tools in your in
your workflows. So reading about new
tools and testing them out, I think, is
a good way to kind of make sure that you
stay on top and kind of plan to be part
of a more modern development cycle going
forward.
Right. And can you share any examples
where testers have taken on new
responsibilities as autonomous testing
was implemented in that company?
The example I said earlier in the
beginning where we had a team of a
larger team of QA engineers that was
kind of downscaled. Those that were were
left in the team needed to spend a lot
of time on on both manual and kind of
scripting out autonomous tests. and they
have seen quite large difference in in
the time that they need to spend on
these things. So they can instead focus
more on planning out and kind of working
with the test suite and understanding
how to how to test the application in a
better way not so much time spending on
maintenance and and repeatable tasks.
Right? So move from maintaining test
suits to more to do more activities like
planning and looking at edge cases or
exploratory testing. Yeah, exactly. And
and working with together with the
development teams to to make sure that
quality is kind of part of the entire
development cycle.
From the discussion we have had, I've
coming I'm coming out with a opinion
that it's not truly autonomous. we still
have a journey to progress towards true
autonomy. So, it's more like
semi-autonomous. Would you agree with
that statement? I would agree with that
statement. I think AI is not really
there yet to be functioning on the same
level as a human on these tasks. So I
think you still have that there's a lot
of work that can be kind of offloaded to
AI but I still think you need a human to
kind of understand and think about how
to run your test suites and how to make
sure that the application is actually
functioning as you tend to. Right. Well,
that's been an incredibly insightful
discussion on autonomous testing. Before
we wrap up, do you have any final
thoughts or advice for teams looking to
adopt autonomous testing?
I think you should embrace the new
changes that are happening with open
arms. I think there is a lot of fear and
kind of skepticism around AI development
today. But I think we will see uh large
improvements over the next coming years.
And I think it will be superpower to
have these AI capable tools in your tool
belt. Even if you're a develop normal
developer, if you're kind of a QA
engineer or QA tester, I think it will
be a bright future. So stay curious and
and continue to learn.
Thank you Wilhelm for coming on the
show. It's been a real pleasure. Thank
you. This is British Amanut for Software
Engineering Radio. Thank you for
listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.